<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Walking With Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-06T20:21:32+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Paul Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Big ride around the Peak District]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2012/05/13/big-ride-around-the-peak-district/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2012/05/13/big-ride-around-the-peak-district</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, over a year has passed since I last posted. Don&#8217;t worry, I have still been walking, although not as much in the hills as in the past. However I have been riding my mountain bike a lot. This has increased even more so over the last couple of months as a couple of mates and I train for our first <a title="Welsh Ride Thing" href="http://welshridething.blogspot.com/">Welsh Ride Thing</a> attempt in June.</p>

<p>Well, yesterday, I broke the 20 mile ride for the first time this year. I followed the Hope Tour route from the Vertebrate Graphics White Peak book. 22 miles, and &gt; 1000 metres to climb was the target, and my singlespeed Orange P7 the weapon.</p>

<p><a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/photo.jpg"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-325" title="Mam Tor ridge from Hope Cross" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/photo.jpg" alt="Mam Tor ridge from Hope Cross" width="500" height="292" /></a></p>

<p>I was out of the house early so I could start riding around 9am, leaving the main car park at Hope, Derbyshire. The weather was beautiful, though slightly cold - this would be perfect for the drag up past Win Hill to Hope Cross. Riding at my own pace, it actually went quiet well and whilst I did get off and push for the steeper sections, my 20 tooth rear cog allowed me to ride most of the climb.</p>

<p>Over the top, and there&#8217;s my favourite descent of the Peak District down to Rowlee Farm. Rocky descents where momentum is your friend is one area where the low ratio gear caused problems. I could not maintain the speed I&#8217;d have liked to, and thus my legs and arms got more of a pounding than if I could have pedalled through it. I had to stop a couple of times just to give my limbs a rest!!</p>

<p>Over the A57, and I actually managed to clean the climb out of Rowlee Farm and was delighted to get the top for the descent past Lockerbrook Farm to the reservoirs. I managed to ride past Fairholmes without stopped for a pastie and was soon climbing (well pushing) up the steep bridleway back up towards the crossroad above Hagg Farm. I met a great couple half way up that I actually rode with for most of the remaining miles. The drop to Hagg Farm is another classic, I really love my P7, and am so glad I recently sorted the seat post out&#8230;</p>

<p>Over the A57, and after another short downhill blast comes the pain. A long slog along the reservoirs, then up and over the flanks of Win Hill takes you to Thornhill and my riding nemesis - Aston. I hate Aston. Yes it&#8217;s a pretty little hamlet and beautiful surroundings. But it&#8217;s always the signal for a painful drag up Win Hill, and this was the 3rd time my bike was pointing towards the sky on Win Hill today. This last climb took me within 300 yards of Hope Cross, and after 18 miles or so, it wasn&#8217;t a great warm down. At least at the top, you get the chance to point the bike back down the hill down the slightly rocky though disappointing straight downhill back into Hope.</p>

<p>As I rode back toward town, I stopped suddenly to help a Duke of Edinburgh student who had collapsed. She was been looked after by local walker but unsure whether they could get an accurate call through to the emergency services, I rode into Hope and reported the incident from 18 Bikes.</p>

<p>I finally managed to reaquiant myself with the car about 3pm. 5 and a half hours I&#8217;d spent in the saddle, and boy, does my back end know about it!! In fact, when home in evening, I started researching Sudocream and chamois creams - I&#8217;m not looking forward to the 3 day event in Wales anymore!!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alport Castles from Fairholmes]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2011/02/13/alport-castles-from-fairholmes/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2011/02/13/alport-castles-from-fairholmes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a while. A while since I&#8217;ve blogged about walking that is. And well, it&#8217;s mainly because it&#8217;s been a while since I&#8217;ve hill walked. I&#8217;ve been doing lot&#8217;s of local walks recently, but yesterday was my first hill of the year.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;alignnone&#8221; width=&#8221;500&#8221; caption=&#8221;B &amp; W Gate near the top of the wood above Fairholmes&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/5441625599/"><img title="B &amp; W Gate near the top of the wood above Fairholmes" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5019/5441625599_8262ac14ab.jpg" alt="B &amp; W Gate near the top of the wood above Fairholmes" width="500" height="333" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;alignright&#8221; width=&#8221;159&#8221; caption=&#8221;Wood near Derwent Reservoir&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/5441590653/"><img title="Wood near Derwent Reservoir" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5253/5441590653_5c20bdf07a_m.jpg" alt="Wood near Derwent Reservoir" width="159" height="240" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The plan this year is for a decent Peak District or similar walk every other week, and yesterday Cheryl and I walked from the Fairholmes car park on the edge of the Derwent Reservoir up to Alport Castles - my first time to the Castles and my first time walking up this side of the reservoir. It was a really pleasant day. Yeah, it rained at the stop, and just after lunch, but it wasn&#8217;t too warm or cold, and the varying weather made for great photos. Being our first hill walk for a while, we deliberately kept the miles low but were fine at the end.</p>

<p>The highlight of the day for me was seeing the water fall over both dams on the reservoir. The sound was impressive, and I was hoping to try some slow shutter speed photography, but I had forgotten my ND filters and there was just too much light for this. The walk along the eastern shores was much more interesting than the other side, with lots of interest; waterfalls, still ponds and old village ruins. We agreed that we must revisit in April to see the rhododendrons blossom.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;alignnone&#8221; width=&#8221;500&#8221; caption=&#8221;Sun behind cloud&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/5441624371/"><img title="Sun behind cloud" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5251/5441624371_1dfc63e7fc.jpg" alt="Sun behind cloud" width="500" height="332" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The walk up from the reservoir to the castles wasn&#8217;t too bad, and we enjoyed sandwiches on the edge, looking over the next valley. Even spotted some wildcampers in the valley below, though at midday, this was a little late to strike pitch!</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve <a title="Alport Castles from Fairholmes Flickr set" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/sets/72157625914429359/">uploaded some photos</a> from the day, and promise to both hill walk, and update this site more frequently. I promise!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday's Matlock biking epic]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/31/yesterdays-matlock-biking-epic/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/31/yesterdays-matlock-biking-epic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Decided on a bike ride in the Peak District for Saturday. A quick scan through my <a title="White Peak Mountain Biking" href="http://www.v-publishing.co.uk/titles/index/white-peak-mountain-biking-the-pure-trails.html">White Peaks book</a> led to a planned Cromford Circuit ride - about 21k. As I was on my own for the day, and in such a beautiful place, I decidied to get up their early and have a play with the camera over at Black Rocks which was good.<!--more-->I finished with the camera about 9 so changed, padded up and started riding about 9:30. This is where my first navigational blunder occurred. I cycled about 2 miles the wrong way down the High Peak Trail. Doh! Having realised my mistake, I climbed onto the A6 and backtracked to Cromford to start the second loop of the figure of eight route. This was fairly uneventful, lots of climbing and descending easy, but pretty trails and a few cow pat scattered fields.</p>

<p>On completing this loop, I continues to start again, from Black Rocks. Having joined up on the High Peak Trail again, things got a little tougher. My first climb that I couldn&#8217;t complete on the singlespeed was embarrasing - especially when some older people overtooks me as I pushed - they did have gears though!!</p>

<p>Then, just having overtaken some walkers, I realised that I had overshot the bridleway exit from this trail. So, I had to backtrack again, past the walkers. Doh again! By this time, with my errors, time was getting on, so I needed to pick up the pace. It&#8217;s a vicious circle however, the less I look at the route guide / map, the more I missed turns etc. I was reminded of a couple of the negatives to natural trail riding - navigation and farm gates spoil &#8216;the flow&#8217; of the ride no end - especially during fast descents.</p>

<p>There was one more lesson to learn however - keep your mouth closed when descending fast tarmac after riding through cow pats. I forgot at one point, and was reminded when a sugar cube piece of turd flew off my front tyre straight into my gob. I was travelling too fast and concentrating too hard to spit. Mind, I did need the calories. To add injury to insult, the final descent into Matlock included a &#8216;cheeky trail&#8217; comprising of singletrack through a nettle field. My ankles are still itchy now&#8230;</p>

<p>All in all, it was a good day. My legs and arms ache, still not fit enough for singlespeeding in the Peaks really. And the photography was  more successful than the navigation. But I did have some big (yes, the open mouth again) grins on the descents! I wonder what next weekend will deliver.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ ]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/29/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crackpot done]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/25/crackpot-done/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/25/crackpot-done</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_280&#8221; align=&#8221;alignright&#8221; width=&#8221;112&#8221; caption=&#8221;Keep left, keep left&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/keep-left-keep-left.jpg"><img class="size-thumbnail wp-image-280" title="Keep left, keep left" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/keep-left-keep-left.jpg?w=112" alt="Keep left, keep left" width="112" height="150" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>My last <a title="Yorkshire bound for Booze and Crackpot" href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/2010/10/22/yorkshire-bound/">post</a> on Friday suggested that Chris and I rode at least the <a title="Booze and Crackpot round, Swaledale" href="http://www.yorkshiredales.org.uk/mtb-home/mtb-findaroute/mtb-route-boozecrackpot.htm">Crackpot</a> loop from the <a title="Dales Bike Centre" href="http://www.dalesbikecentre.co.uk/">Dales Bike Centre</a> on Saturday. Well, about 10 minutes after I posted, Chris arrived at my home, we swiftly transfered his stuff to my car and off with shot. Well, for about 20 minutes until we hit traffic at Nottingham, Mansfield, Chesterfield, Sheffield, you get the picture. Things weren&#8217;t looking good for early arrival and pub meal up in Grinton. However, after passing Sheffield, suddely the traffic dispersed and we motored on through the Dales.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>On arrival at about 8, a quick call to the Dales Bike Centre&#8217;s owner got us the key, and entry to a 4 bunk room - luckily we managed to get this to ourselves as there was only two other people in the whole place that night. A quick walk upto the Bridge Inn got us some decent pub grub washed down with my first Oxford Gold and a Thatchers Gold.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_279&#8221; align=&#8221;alignleft&#8221; width=&#8221;150&#8221; caption=&#8221;He looks so happy, he doesn&#039;t know the size of the next hill!!&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/hey.jpg"><img class="size-thumbnail wp-image-279 " title="Chris before the hill" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/hey.jpg?w=150" alt="Chris before the hill" width="150" height="112" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>After an early to bed, and rise, we enjoyed a nice bacon sarnie for carb loading before setting off on the bikes about 9:30. The bridleway that parrallels the River Swale was easy to follow, although provided some fun where the Swale has broken it&#8217;s banks and swalled some of the path. Water was getting on for a foot deep; great fun to ride through, though hub bearings probably didn&#8217;t feel that way.</p>

<p>Only once the river is left does the real work begin, climbing (sometimes riding, sometimes pushing) through Crackpot, then Summer Lodge and finally to the singletrack road at the top of the hill. As we were knackered at this point, it seemed a good idea to break for lunch. Bad mistake, gloves off meant hands got very cold due to driving wind, ~5 degrees temp and drizzle. Infact, it took a good 45 minutes for them to finally warm enough to use brakes properly and getting feeling back into them.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_281&#8221; align=&#8221;alignright&#8221; width=&#8221;150&#8221; caption=&#8221;The pain in my legs, so bad&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/it-hurts.jpg"><img class="size-thumbnail wp-image-281 " title="God, it hurts" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/it-hurts.jpg?w=150" alt="The pain in my legs, so bad" width="150" height="112" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Unfortunately, about 2 miles after the road section, we took a slight detour from the plan; following the first distinct path up towards High Harker Hill. This was a mistake, it was not the bridleway, but rather a grouse shooting track, and wound steeply for 1/2 a mile before terminating at a peat bog. We didn&#8217;t want to backtrack and lose the height we had gained, so we treked for about a mile across the bog to re-join the bridleway correctly to High Harker Hill.</p>

<p>From here, some decent fast rocky, then moorland descents contoured down the hill, finally arriving at the road we had driven down the night before. A sharp climb up this took us to a fairly boring farmland descent back to Grinton.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_289&#8221; align=&#8221;alignleft&#8221; width=&#8221;150&#8221; caption=&#8221;Chris&#039;s muddy feet&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/chriss-muddy-feet.jpg"><img class="size-thumbnail wp-image-289" title="Chris's muddy feet" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/chriss-muddy-feet.jpg?w=150" alt="Chris's muddy feet" width="150" height="112" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Once back, we used the bike wash facilities, scrubbed up and left with cameras, bound for Reeth for some photography. This didn&#8217;t really work out, although we did visit a great outdoors shop - <a title="Swaledale Outdoors" href="http://en-gb.facebook.com/pages/Reeth-United-Kingdom/Swaledale-Outdoors-Shop-Reeth/403252822246">Swaledale Outdoors</a>. They had a good mix of lightweight clothes and equipment and tried on some Inov-8 Terroc 330s - my next walking trainers when I start wearing trainers again (maybe next spring).</p>

<p>After the walk around Reeth, we returned to the bike centre, jumped in my car and headed off to Hawes for a curry, stopping off at the large cairn on Buttertubs for some late evening photography. I enjoyed my Chicken Tikka Saag and the return to the Bridge Inn for a pint of Crag Rat and a whiskey. We returned to the bike centre early, maybe 10ish, to grab some sleep before getting up at 3:30am  Sunday to beeline over to Stanage Edge in the Peak District to get some <a title="My first photographic sunrise" href="http://thephotographic.me.uk/?p=24">sunrise photos</a> - much better results than Saturday&#8217;s photographic exploits. Then home.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yorkshire bound for Booze and Crackpot]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/22/yorkshire-bound/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/10/22/yorkshire-bound</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here we go, first natural mountain bike ride for a couple of months. Been talking about a weekender with Chris, an ex colleage and fellow mtber for a while. Snowdonia was a comman theme, but in the end, Chris suggested a circuit of Swaledale, Yorkshire as detailed in a magazine. He also mentioned the <a title="The Dales Bike Centre" href="http://www.dalesbikecentre.co.uk/">Dales Bike Centre</a> at Grinton as the obvious place to stay. So with about 2 seconds of thought, we booked up for this weekend.</p>

<p>I have been trying to train for this circuit, as my bike is currently in singlespeed mode; not ideal for any Dales ride, and the Peak District <a title="Hope Triple 8" href="http://www.mountainbikerides.co.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;catid=1:the-peak-district&amp;id=14:hope-triple-eight&amp;Itemid=2">Hope Triple 8</a> circuit was a great start.  Similar gradients, abeit smaller hills were a challenge, but I did clean 2 of the 6, and rode significant portions of another 2. However, since then, I have suffered a little with the knee, but after some physio and Cannock Follow the Dog / Monkey Trail laps, I think I am just about ready.</p>

<p>The last couple of weeks, a little further planning has been done. After the Dales Bike Centre suggested few singlespeed compatible circuits, we have decided on the southern loop of the <a title="Booze and Crackpot Round of Swaledale" href="http://www.mtbthedales.org.uk/mtb-home/mtb-findaroute/mtb-route-boozecrackpot.htm">Booze and Crackpot</a> round of Swaledale, possibly extending to the northern loop if legs, backs and cake supplies allow.  Of particular interest to me will be my recent conversion to flat pedals; hopefully a little caution and my 661 pads will get me down in one piece&#8230;</p>

<p>We&#8217;ll be leaving the Midlands this evening, and hopefully dining at the Bridge Inn, Grinton this evening. Returning Sunday afternoon, with the non biking gaps filled with some photography, and beer drinking - well, we do have to rehydrate!!</p>

<p>Pics and report to follow&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to organize my Flickr photos]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/25/how-to-organize-my-flickr-photos/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/25/how-to-organize-my-flickr-photos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, here&#8217;s a post about photography but with no photos&#8230; I am currently thinking about how to organise my Flickr account to acheive two goals:</p>

<p>1) To support my blog&#8217;s stories about hill walking, wildcamping etc.</p>

<p>2) To showcase my hopefully improving photographic skills.</p>

<p>The problem is that often, these goals are at odds&#8230;.</p>

<p>To fulfil a showcase, I should only publish photos that I believe to be both technically good, and also aesthetically pleasing. The problem with this is that for example, during my recent weekend in Snowdonia, only 5 or six photos taken met these characteristics.</p>

<p>Now, on the other hand, to support my hill walking posts, I often want to upload most photos from a day. Even if I don&#8217;t embed the photos in a post, I would probably be best to link to a Flickr collection at the bottom of the post. Now, many of these photos are only snaps, sometimes only from the iPhone, in the midday sun with little thought to photography.</p>

<p>Oh hum, maybe another glass of wine and a sleep will shed some light on this problem&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Snowdon training prep - done!!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/13/snowdon-training-prep-done/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/13/snowdon-training-prep-done</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, what a wonderful weekend. Sun didn&#8217;t stop shining and worst weather related problem was the air conditioning failing on my car when driving to Snowdonia - must get it recharged. Anyhow, plan for the weekend was to scoot over to Caernarfon Friday afternoon and have a go at Snowdon Saturday.</p>

<p>It would be rude to drive through Betws-y-Coed without doing a little outdoors shopping, and I surprised myself by only coming away with a Mountain Hardware shirt. The drive then across the A5 cheered us up - only a little snow was left on Snowdon so all looked good for Saturday. We rounded the day off with a pleasant meal in Caernarfon and an early night.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;199&#8221; caption=&#8221;Yachts in Doc Fictoria, Caernarfon&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/4515792196/in/set-72157623716328093/"><img class=" " title="Yachts in Doc Fictoria, Caernarfon" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2775/4515792196_5137c88402.jpg" alt="Yachts in Doc Fictoria, Caernarfon" width="199" height="300" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Saturday morning, we fueled up at Macdonalds, then drove over to Llamberis parking right at the foot of Snowdon. Think we got the last spot in the car park. Then was started the walk. It was real hot, and I always struggle in the heat. Sure enough, by the half way house, I was pleased with my choice of shorts and short sleeved t-shirt given the mocking I had all morning.</p>

<p>A quick stop at the Halfway House for more water, and we continued to climb eventually reaching snow level at the higher tunnel under the railway. The snow was easily overcome, or sidestepped; I wish I had tried my fell running shoes for the first time this year. Before we summited, we found amusement at how people were tackling the icy shoot between the plateau and the top of the Pyg Track - mainly on their bottoms.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;People slidding down to descend Pyg Track / Miner&#039;s Path&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/4515176089/in/set-72157623716328093/"><img class=" " title="People slidding down to descend Pyg Track / Miner's Path" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2761/4515176089_c7a312f7f7.jpg" alt="People slidding down to descend Pyg Track / Miner's Path" width="300" height="200" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>We summited about 13:00 and dropped over the other side of the hill towards the Snowdon Rangers path to find some tranquility to enjoy lunch. It really did feel like summer, even at the top.</p>

<p>We then returned over the summit, but as we dropped past the new building, we saw a search and rescue helicopter hovering above Crib Goch. We feared the worst, but speculated that it would be OK - the helicopter seemed to be right over the ridge rather than to a side - and thus a fall. Unfortunately, Sunday morning we learned that a guy had a suspected heart attack - our sympathies go out to his family and friends. A little subdued, we continued the descent which went pretty quickly and uneventfully.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Tree on Snowdon&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/4515192981/in/set-72157623716328093/"><img class=" " title="Tree on Snowdon" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2720/4515192981_38970a43a9.jpg" alt="Tree on Snowdon" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>On arrival at Llamberis, we quickly dispatched ice creams and drove back to Caernarfon for a MASSIVE chinese banquet. I am sure we undid all the good work done, but it was worth it.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Log above river&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/4515228497/in/set-72157623716328093/"><img title="Log above river" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2764/4515228497_6b460ee5db.jpg" alt="Log above river" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Sunday morning saw a more leisurely walk along the Afon Llugwy to Swallow Falls from Betws-y-Coed. I must be getting better as I entered Cotswold Outdoors and I didn&#8217;t even buy anything!!! The weekend was rounded off with burger and chips at a pub in the village. All in all, a great weekend though we must surely pay for the great weather with some rain&#8230;</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;500&#8221; caption=&#8221;Tributary of Afon Llugwy&#8221;]<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/goatifiedcreature/4515871134/in/set-72157623716328093/"><img title="Tributary of Afon Llugwy" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2780/4515871134_e7fbd6423e.jpg" alt="Tributary of Afon Llugwy" width="500" height="331" /></a>[/caption]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Easter Buttermere visit]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/05/easter-buttermere-visit/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/04/05/easter-buttermere-visit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months ago, I booked train tickets to Windermere for my first wildcamp of 2010. Initial plans were to hostel at Windermere Wednesday night, then bus to Langdale, walk to and camp on Haystacks, then Dale Head and finally end up in Keswick for the bus back to windermere Saturday morning. However, due to the forecast snow and gales, I chickened out of camping, and instead chose to hostel at Buttermere.</p>

<p>Thus, after an excellent journey and sleep Wednesday, I found myself Thursday morning bussing to Buttermere Youth Hostel. This journey was an experience. Started with heavy snow on Dunmail Raise, just missing photographing an extremely low flying plane over Thirlmere, and confirmation of the amount of snow lying on the hills. Then, the next bus journey saw us put a BMW into a fence near Catbells, and a slippy ascent of Honister Pass.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_187&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Views from the Buttermere Rambler&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100401-dsc_00461.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-187" title="Views from the Buttermere Rambler" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100401-dsc_00461.jpg?w=300" alt="Views from the Buttermere Rambler" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Anyhow, finally, Thursday lunchtime I decided the afternoon wouldn&#8217;t give enough time for an ascent on Haystacks, especially as I hadn&#8217;t got an up to date weather forecast, so instead, I took a walk around Buttermere lake. I did spice up the low level walk with some scrambling up the two waterfalls at base of Red Pike and High Crag - all in the name of photography ;) Thursday evening saw a lively chat with a youth hostel room mate, a beef burger and a few beers and double Jura single malts.</p>

<p>Friday morning, and I was up early. After breakfast, I walked along the SE shore of Buttermere to the bottom of Haystacks, and started climbing towards Scarth Gap. Nearing the top, I had to choose whether to go all out along High Crag towards Red Pike or be sensible and just bite of Haystacks. I choose the latter, mainly as snow and low visibility was forecast for around 14:00.</p>

<p>The ascent of Haystacks was ok; the large rock steps were covered by fresh snow which gave good enough grip although a few sections did look tricky for the descent. Infact, following the main path over the cairns was difficult when entering the rocky sections. Several down climbs on icy steps nearly forced a rethink and retreat, but no, I scrambled down and evently reached Innominate Tarn about 11:00.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_188&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Innominate Tarn and the nameless tarn on Haystacks&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_00911.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-188" title="Innominate Tarn and the nameless tarn on Haystacks" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_00911.jpg?w=300" alt="Innominate Tarn and the nameless tarn on Haystacks" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The scenery was fantastic, the snowy Gables and Pillar dominating the vista with the tarns providing perfect subjects for photography. I wanted to get the tripod out, and play with filters etc. However, a huge black cloud was incoming from Borrowdale, and I feared this might bring snow, a white-out or general hill fog, so I continued with some hand held shots and thus allowed me to descend shortly after.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_189&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;A tarn on Haystacks&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_00931.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-189" title="A tarn on Haystacks" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_00931.jpg?w=300" alt="A tarn on Haystacks" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>It was on descending the rocky summit of Haystacks that my heavy rucksack (the DSLR, tripod, crampons, axe and winter clothing a light sack does not make) gave me the biggest problems. My centre of gravity was way off, the the rucksack did it&#8217;s best to pull me of the slippy but sure handholds when scrambling down the icy steps. Also, my Scarpa SLs providing great problems in keeping traction in compacted snow, I definately seemed to slip more frequently than others around.</p>

<p>Upon descending to Scarth Gap, I took a left to a rocky outcrop that provided a perfect view to upper and lower Ennerdale. The High Level Route on Pillar stuck out in the snow so clearly, and it was supprising how much more snow was on the valley floor than in the neighbouring Buttermere.A re-ascent of Scarth Gap and uneventful descent back to Buttermere followed.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_190&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Wild and snowy Ennerdale&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_01251.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-190" title="Wild and snowy Ennerdale" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100402-dsc_01251.jpg?w=300" alt="Wild and snowy Ennerdale" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Last time I walked down this hill, I nearly cried with pain due to my knee, and I waited and waited for a reshow. But now, the knee was ok, even with the weight I was carrying. Infact, the only thing I really noticed was my lack of hill fitness - infact the largest hill I have done in 2010 was a leisurely paced Whernside.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_191&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Views towards Dale Head from Buttermere&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100403-dsc_02091.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-191" title="Views towards Dale Head from Buttermere" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/04/20100403-dsc_02091.jpg?w=300" alt="Views towards Dale Head from Buttermere" width="300" height="166" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>However, peak bagging will soon pick up. April will bring Snowdon twice. Then Scafell Pike, Nevis and two other Munros are the aim of May&#8217;s Scotland holiday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shock! Horror! A Peak District walk without a hill!]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/28/shock-horror-a-peak-district-walk-without-a-hill/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/28/shock-horror-a-peak-district-walk-without-a-hill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it had to happen someday. A visit to the Peak District without the aim of climbing a hill. We had planned all week to visit the Peaks with Nick from work. Also, having done a fair amount of ascent recently, Cheryl also suggested a longer but flattish walk. So a quick visit to <a title="Walking Britain website" href="http://www.walkingbritain.co.uk/">Walking Britain</a> and a walk from Monyash to Lathkill Dale was chosen.</p>

<p>Nick picked us up about 10ish, so we walked out of Monyash about 11. The first couple of miles were incident free, other than some piss taking out of my shorts - their 2nd outing this year! I must admit I was a little chilly&#8230;</p>

<p>Things went slightly amis however, when we descended into Caves Dale. We should have climbed straight out of it again to head over to Youlgreave, but alas, I wasn&#8217;t concentrating on the map, and thus beared left into Lathkill Dale. This valley should have been the return leg, but instead we choose to walk down it.</p>

<p>Its a great valley, smaller and less dramatic than Dove Dale, but it did feel more remote, and dare I say, more pretty. There was green moss growing on just about every wall and tree. There were beautiful waterfalls (some man made) so I bored my companions a little by rattling off about 300 photos. Oops!</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_182&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Waterfalls on the River Lathkill&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_0038.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-182" title="20100328-DSC_0038" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_0038.jpg?w=300" alt="Waterfalls on the River Lathkill" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Then, we continued further downstream to a point where the valley opened up. We sat, eat lunch and watched ducks fight and dive in the river. A little further down the stream on Conksbury Bridge, I saw my first live trout - there were loads of them.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_183&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Trout in the River Lathkill&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_0199.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-183" title="20100328-DSC_0199" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_0199.jpg?w=300" alt="Trout in the River Lathkill" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>After some consideration at the bridge, we decided to take the shorter option back to Monyash by simple retracing our steps through Lathkill Dale right to the end. So we did, and a very pleasent walk back it was. It&#8217;s amazing how different the views are looking through a valley one direction and the other. Then, once we entered the section above Caves Dale, the terrain got a little tougher, and it became more obvious were were in limestone country. Lots of caves, and limestone crags providing quite dramatic views. This upper section takes you to within a mile of Monyash, so after some simple trekking over a couple of farmer&#8217;s fields, we arrived in Monyash about 17:00. We found a cafe on the way back to the car and polished off toffee and chocolate ripple ice creams - the first outdoors ice creams of the year.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_184&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Limestone features in the top of Lathkill Dale&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_03171.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-184" title="20100328-DSC_0317" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100328-dsc_03171.jpg?w=300" alt="Limestone features in the top of Lathkill Dale" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p id="__mce"><br /></p>


<p>All in all, a great walk and the weather was ok. Unfortunately, as blogged yesterday, snow is forecast for my lakeland expedition but at least my YHA bookings are now confirmed at Windermere, Buttermere and Keswick. Just got to plan the route between them!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do I do to the weather...]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/27/what-do-i-do-to-the-weather/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/27/what-do-i-do-to-the-weather</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cheryl&#8217;s mom and I have a running joke that whenever I plan a lakeland trip without Cheryl, I turn the weather sour&#8230;</p>

<p>Well, after last Sunday&#8217;s beautiful spring walk, I had my hopes up for a great solo backpack and wildcamp from Langdale.</p>

<p>I spent my lunch breaks this week constructing a stove windshield and pot cosy. I spent this morning in the garage strugging but finally succeeding in packing my stuff into my OMM 35L rucksack except for the tent, that fits great into the &#8216;Multi Sport Compressor&#8217;&#8230; Pack weight including water and food - 18lb; not bad at all.</p>

<p>Then, I spent much of this afternoon planning the route in finer detail. Done.</p>

<p>Or so I thought. About 4 o&#8217;clock, I looked at the bbc weather report to decide whether tomorrows ramble would be White Peaks or Shropshire. BBC weather said it would be fine in both places. But from the corner of my eye, I spotted snow forecast Wednesday. I had already seen a possible snow shower forest cast the usually pessimistic MWIS, but now the BBC!!</p>

<p>Further searched for weather locally, and yeah, heavy snow Tuesday night through Wednesday.</p>

<p>When I mentioned all this to Cheryl, I was about to say &#8216;I ain&#8217;t wildcamping at the top of a mountain next week, maybe I will wimp out and use a campsite&#8230;&#8217; but she interrupted suggesting that I will wimp out and use a youth hostel.</p>

<p>There is was, a seed planted. A couple of quick calls, and hopefully I will get accommodation in Buttermere and Keswick.</p>

<p>Now, all I need to do Tuesday night is replace my sleeping bag / tent in the rucksack with crampons and the ice axe!!! Oh, and fully winter gloves, hat and thermals.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1/2 Edale Skyline attempt]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/21/12-edale-skyline-attempt/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/21/12-edale-skyline-attempt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Had a great day in Edale with Cheryl and the pre sister / brother-in-laws (coach trip quote if anyone is sad enough to watch it -no? just me..) . We tried to do a 10 miler  a couple of weeks ago, but the foot of snow put paid to that - tough walking and a possible scary descent of jacob&#8217;s ladder proved too much. So today, we set the matter straight with an attack on 1/2 of the Edale Skyline. The plan: Edale &gt; Hollins Cross &gt; Lose Hill &gt; Hope Cross &gt; Crookstone Knoll &gt; Ringing Roger &gt; Edale.</p>

<p>Now, I got a little ribbing today about my optimistic choice of shorts and a short sleeve shirt; it might be too cold and &#8216;what are those pieces of string hanging out of my shorts&#8217; (i.e. my legs&#8230;). I had my doubts about the choice early morning, mist and only 4 degrees in the car, and this remaining 1/2 way up the M1. Luckily, approaching Chesterfield, BBC weathers predictions came true, and the car&#8217;s thermometer rose to 10 degrees.</p>

<p>Arriving in Edale at about 10:30, we luckily managed to find a prime lay-by parking space only 100 metres out of the village car park. A quick change of clothes and we ascending Hollin&#8217;s Cross, and then Lose Hill. All fairly pleasent, and we enjoyed watching the <span style="text-decoration:line-through;">nutters</span> fell runners competing in some kind of race. We particularly enjoyed one guy appearing to totally cut a corner, not sure whether this was allowed though he did it right in front of a marshall&#8230;The descent of Lose Hill was quick and pain free with the mandatory M&amp;S sarnies half way down. Cheers for the pork pies Steve!!!</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_174&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Edge of Kinder Scout from Crookstone Knoll&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_0078.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-174" title="Edge of Kinder Scout from Crookstone Knoll" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_0078.jpg?w=300" alt="Edge of Kinder Scout from Crookstone Knoll" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>We then started our second hill of the day skirting Win Hill, ascending the roman road to Hope Cross we got our muscles warmed up again for the hard pull up Crookstone Knoll. A few people on rock photos and Percy Pigs refueled us for the &#8216;flat&#8217; walk along the edge to Ringing Roger. Now, by this time, I was happy to see some cloud come in. Firstly, this cooled things down (see, the shorts were a good idea..) and secondly, they reduced the glare from a powerful sun and brought interest to some moody moorland photos. Played for the first time with my stronger grad filter. Maybe OTT for strength but I enjoyed a couple of photos.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_175&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Strange light over the vale of Edale from Ringing Roger&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_01141.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-175" title="Strange light over the vale of Edale from Ringing Roger" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_01141.jpg?w=300" alt="Strange light over the vale of Edale from Ringing Roger" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Finally, we descended Ringing Roger, avoided any pubs in Edale and returned to the car by about 17:00. A tough day - tougher than the nominal 10.3 miles (10.2 if it wasn&#8217;t for a &#8216;navigational occurrence&#8217; by me) with &gt; 600 metres; not bad for the peak district.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_176&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Steve was obviously getting excited about the prospect of beer in Edale ;)&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_00811.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-176" title="Steve enjoying a solitary break away at the front" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100321-dsc_00811.jpg?w=300" alt="" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Even managed a Toby Carvery for dinner, turkey, yorkies and a pint of Bulmers. Nice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few piccies from drive to work]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/11/a-few-piccies-from-drive-to-work/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/11/a-few-piccies-from-drive-to-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the drive to work earlier this week, I noticed the great early morning light falling on the church in Lullington - a village I drive through. This morning, I noticed snow drops starting to appear. I often carry my camera in the car boot, so I decided to park up, get the camera out and rattle off a hundred snaps or so.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_165&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;All Saint&#039;s Church, Lullington, Derbyshire&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00081.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-165" title="All Saint's Church, Lullington, Derbyshire" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00081.jpg?w=300" alt="All Saint's Church, Lullington, Derbyshire" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>I have enjoyed some architectural photography recently, but I was disappointed at this mornings attempts with the church. I struggled to get far enough away to get the church in context and the pics came out a little shallow. I also failed to capture the great light, but maybe next time&#8230;. Also, the sky was perfect blue - a little bland so I will try shooting again with an interesting cloud backdrop.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_166&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;A snow drop in the church yard&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00531.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-166" title="A snow drop in the church yard" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00531.jpg?w=300" alt="A snow drop in the church yard" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Instead, I had a play with some flower shots and quite liked the results for the small amount of time invested. I am now getting to grips with depth of field, and in particular how I could get bokeh effects at smaller apertures than I originally thought.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_167&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;A lone crocus in a field of snow drops&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00591.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-167" title="A lone crocus in a field of snow drops" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100311-dsc_00591.jpg?w=300" alt="A lone crocus in a field of snow drops" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Anyhow, an enjoyable drive to work, and was a little disappointed that on the drive home, I saw a buzzard sitting on a fence next to the road. I would have stopped to get some pictures at close range, but the road had no parking cones due to the Basra Memorial Wall opening at the National Memorial Arboretum.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great day over Edale]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/08/great-day-over-edale/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/08/great-day-over-edale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Had a great day with my future sister and brother in law yesterday in the Edale Valley. Got up there in decent time and arrived in Edale around 11am. Unfortunately, this is a little late on a Sunday to get a parking space. However, we were lucky enough that as we left the car park, a dog walker had just arrived back at his car. Lucky!</p>

<p>Anyway, after  a quick change of footwear and application of gaiters, we started walking up Grindsbrook and beared right towards Ringing Roger. The pull up was steep, and hard work in the strong sun, but after 30 mins we got up to the top of Ringing Roger. From here, the gradient got less but it was quite hard walking up to the edges due to the snow on steep ground. We finally neared the trig point near Ringing Roger about 12 and walked west towards Grindsbrook Clough.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_159&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Nearing the top of the edge&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100307-dsc_00021.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-159" title="Nearing the top of the edge" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100307-dsc_00021.jpg?w=300" alt="Nearing the top of the edge" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Finding the path was difficult, and we had a few moments putting feet into 2 foot deep soft snow holes,  but once the path was found, speed increased. We stopped around 1/2 way along the edge to some rocks which made an excellent place for lunch. It was now nearing 13:30 and the decision was to turn south over Grindslow Knoll, rather than continue the original plan of reaching the top of Jacob&#8217;s Ladder before descending to Edale. Time was pushing on, and we were a little concerned about how icy Jacob&#8217;s Ladder would be - it was bad a few weeks ago with far less snow on the ground. So the route was cut short a little mileage wise. Still 6 miles done - 2 or so through thick snow so the legs were worked quite hard!</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_160&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Grindslow Knoll - Last summit of the day&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100307-dsc_00251.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-160" title="Grindslow Knoll" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/20100307-dsc_00251.jpg?w=300" alt="Grindslow Knoll" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>A quick round of pints at the Old Nags Head Inn rounded off a great snowy and fantastically clear day. Next proper walk will be in a couple of weeks. Hopefully, the snow will have melted a little so we can up the mileage and ascent - I certainly need to as I have booked train tickets for March 31st to Windermere for a 2 night wildcamp and haven&#8217;t done more than 10 miles in the last 3 or 4 months&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A facebook / wordpress 'mashup' test....]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/08/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/03/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A wintery Whernside]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/02/18/a-wintery-whernside/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/02/18/a-wintery-whernside</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, after a few months constrained really to local walks, the last couple of weeks have been great. Two weeks ago, we managed a walk over Church Stretton, and last Saturday we did Rushup Edge, Brown Knowl (easiest crossing I have ever had due to the icy peat) and descended Jacob&#8217;s Ladder.</p>

<p>This Wednesday, I decided to take the day off from work and try something a little more serious. My original idea was to try my crampons for the first time by ascending one of the snowdonia peaks, but MWIS suggested something else by virtue of heavy snow, hail and thunder. I therefore looked to other mountainous regions and decided upon attempting Whernside and Ingleborough.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_145&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Snowy Whernside&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_00011.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-145 " title="Snowy Whernside" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_00011.jpg?w=300" alt="Snowy Whernside" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>I left the house about 6am, and got upto Ingleton about 9:15 to buy the requisite OS map, having planned the route online. Finally arrived at Ribblehead about 9:45 and whilst packing my rucksack, I got chatting to a friendly local in the car park. As we discussed routes, we started walking together up the east flank of Whernside.</p>

<p>The conversation was interesting, local knowledge adds so much to these walks, I learnt about the effort on redirecting the river down Dentdale, about the shake holes, and the limestone pavements on the foot of Ingleborough. Now, I had orignally intended to finish the chat half walk up the hill, and resume normal solitary walking with my camera. However, time flew as our conversation covered the armed services, politics, and the virtues of vegetarianism (I have given up meat for lent&#8230;). Next thing I know, we are crossing an icy tarn before topping out on the summit. I was surprised to see the 6 foot or so of snow built up against the wall, and the cornice build up.</p>

<p>Once at the summit, I enjoyed an M &amp; S ploughmans sandwich and three bean / cheese wrap before resuming the walk down a decidely rocky artifical stair case. I was a little worried with the ice covered steps, and hoped the gradient wouldn&#8217;t be too much for me knee. But no, I was fine, and felt quite fresh by the time I reached the road.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_146&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Old farmhouse near Whernside summit&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_002311.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-146" title="Old farmhouse near Whernside summit" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_002311.jpg?w=300" alt="Old farmhouse near Whernside summit" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>However, time was not on my side for an ascent of the planned Ingleborough. It was about 14:30 and my walking colleage said it would take a good 3 hours to complete the second hill. This time constraint, combined with the no doubt icy north face descent  led me to the descision to walk over the limestone pavements at the foot of Ingleborought which led to a faint path over fields back to Ribbledale.</p>

<p>[caption id=&#8221;attachment_144&#8221; align=&#8221;aligncenter&#8221; width=&#8221;300&#8221; caption=&#8221;Moody limestone pavement&#8221;]<a href="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_0140.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-144 " title="Moody limestone pavement" src="http://walkingwithwilliams.files.wordpress.com/2010/02/20100217-dsc_0140.jpg?w=300" alt="Moody limestone pavement" width="300" height="179" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>All in all, about 12 miles of walking over 6 hours, followed by an awful 3.5 hour drive down the M6. Still, a fantastic winter walking day, as the photos hopefully show&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Much more photography stuff on the go.]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/01/09/much-more-photography-stuff-on-the-go/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2010/01/09/much-more-photography-stuff-on-the-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it&#8217;s been an interesting few weeks regarding two of my three main hobbies - walking and photography. MTBing is the other one of which I haven&#8217;t done any since Christmas.</p>

<p>No, regarding walking, we have only done local walks of recent, even though we managed to get up to Keswick on my Birthday. However, whilst up there, I suffered a stomach upset so returned the very next day so no walks.</p>

<p>However, I have been putting much effort into photography, my interest being mainly driven by a new Nikon D90 given to me as a joint Birthday / Xmas pressie from the other half and my parents. Since getting the camera, I have been snapping anything and everything and my skills with the camera have come on leaps and bounds. I have spent several evenings recently re-keywording my Lightroom catalogue, and will be refining, tweaking and uploading pictures to Flickr. I am to complete the rest of my pictures by late January. Hopefully, by this time, the roads will be sufficiently clear of snow that my girlfriend will be happy to travel up to the Peak District for our first hill walk of the year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New SLR for Chrimbo delivered....]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/12/27/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/12/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, I have been a little slack recenty with uploads and photos. This is mainly due to th</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Similarities between 'going lightweight' and single speed mountain biking]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/11/28/similarities-between-going-lightweight-and-single-speed-mountain-biking/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/11/28/similarities-between-going-lightweight-and-single-speed-mountain-biking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, as some know and others don&#8217;t, I am one of those dodgy people who both walk the hills, and mountain bike. Many times I have chatted with people in both disciplines, and whilst the vast majority understand the others views and share a liking for outdoors, health etc, I have also seen examples of people with a great dislike for the others hobby. Only August this year, whilst walking up the LLamberis pass, I saw some bikes downhilling having a great time. They were traveling at a fair old pace but as they saw me and the other half, they politely slowed down, and passed on the far side of the pass. With exchanged nods, they continued down until I heard several cries emiting from a group of walkers following us up. They were about 5 in strength and wouldn&#8217;t at least give a little room for the mtbers, and instead hurled abuse at them. Now, it was about 10:30 so offiicially the bikers were in the wrong, but come on&#8230; They must have got up before the break of dawn to heave their steel beasties up the hill. Then for whatever reason, the got a little delayed and came down a little late.  But they were considerate, polite and friendly. But got nothing in return other than abuse.</p>

<p>On the other hand, i have seen many bikers riding down paths crowded with walkers, failing to slowdown and scare the walkers out of their wits.</p>

<p>So one simularity between people participating in both persuits is a subset of idiots.</p>

<p>However, whilst riding my newly converted to singlespeed mountain bike around Cannock Chase, I pondered another similarity - the getting back to basics in both mountain biking and lightweight backpacking. Part of the ethos of lightweight backpacking isn&#8217;t just buying the latest lighter version of the previous light thing. Its also about getting rid of redundant kit, using things for multiple purposes, getting rid of  a few comforts and being a little sadistic. It also lends itself to laziness - not having to carry heavy loads, not having to pack so many things - just walk, camp minimally and walk again the next day.</p>

<p>Now, I can definitely relate to the laziness part, and this in part is why I have discovered single speed mountain biking which is defined as: removing the 300+ quids worth of drivetrain related components and replace them with 1) a single rear cog, 2) a single front chainring and 3) a chain. The main advantage to this regression in functionality is to ease maintenance - no more fine tuning of gears, no more poor shifting or ghost shifts. Less to clean, and that that is left (hubs, bottom bracket shell etc) are far easier to get to. In fact, only this morning I managed to clean the bike properly without having to remove the chain. Bliss.</p>

<p>Now, unfortunately and unlike lightweight backpacking, the 2lb of weight loss brough about from removing this stuff does not translate into an easier bike to ride. I draw a parallel with lightweight stoves not being as fast or as easy to cook on that larger car tent based ones. Uphills are murder, and several downhills can&#8217;t be attacked with the normal gusto, simple because you run out of gears. However,  I still the downs as I sit back and get through them concentrating on momentus and line rather than pendalling my nuts off.</p>

<p>However, I am currently contemplating how these persuites can actually be combined. Gears, and the maintence their off have been one of the main worries about taking to the hills on multiday rides. Too many tools, and spare bits and pieces to carry. And a bike isn&#8217;t the easiest thing to carry if i need to get to a bikeshop for a new derailleur.</p>

<p>But my final similarity for this post relates to the looks from other people. I remember sitting on a train last year talking to another walker. He asked what my lakeland adventure would bring me. I told him I was expecting a 3 day walk over several mountains. He then asked where I would be overnighting. He presumed I would be hosteling etc. as I only had a 35 litre pack. In my tent I explained. But where is it? I noticed this very same confusing look yesterday when I was riding around &#8216;The Dog&#8217; in Cannock. I had got to the top of the biggest hill, and whilst my heart nearly left my chest and I thought I had left my lungs behind, when I approached two guys having a rest they were surprised that I was pushing such a big gear and struggling so much. Then they realised why - I couldn&#8217;t shift down ;(</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update on knee]]></title>
    <link href="http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/11/15/update-on-knee/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walkingwithwilliams.me.uk/blog/2009/11/15/update-on-knee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, phase 2 of my knee test started today.</p>

<p>Test methodology: attempt roughly half of the Edale skyline.</p>

<p>Hypothesis: my knee will work fine, no probs. Today the peaks, tomorrow the world, well several Wainwrights at least.</p>

<p>Observations: 1 nasty car crash, and early morning vista of clag covered tops,  a beautiful day with bucket loads of sun and cooling winds at just the right time. Oh and some crazy remote control kite things. V. cool.</p>

<p>Write up: started from Castleton, and today chose my scarpa sl and gaiters. Had enough of fell running shoes until spring now.</p>

<p>My route started by popping over Hollins  cross and back down to Edale. Then having had a chat with some mtbers, I started the scramble up Grindsbrook Clough. Maybe I was a little silly trying this kind of stuff, especially when I slipped on a slimy rock and ended up hugging a rock for dear life - I nearly ended up in the stream. At the top I turned left and had lunch on Crowden Tower. Nice M&amp;S ham and cheese sarnies!</p>

<p>Now, with the bad weather of recent, my heart rate started to increase as I came to my peat bog nemesis - Brown Knoll. Recollections of being thick down in methane releasing bog and the sight of three lads with peat up to their knees didn&#8217;t help, and I did think several times about chickening out and descending Jacob&#8217;s Ladder.</p>

<p>But now, the plan was set and I continued over the knoll. It wasn&#8217;t too bad up to the trig point but the ground was bad thereafter. Especially dodgy was one horizontal grough that was deceiving - normally vegetation means safe ground, but this grough had much grass yet wouldn&#8217;t take my weight. Luckily, I had been cautious and only put one foot down. As soon as I realised, the foot was out, and I retreated. I succeeded in beating the grough via a little run up and 5ft jump. Again, maybe stupid with the knee but hell, I don&#8217;t like peat.</p>

<p>Once the knoll was complete, the simple but tiring walk over Rushup edge then down the broken road to Castleton concluded a great walking day.</p>

<p>Conclusion 1: I felt no knee pain despite my rough calculations of 13.5 miles and 775 metres of ascent. I think the knee might be on it&#8217;s way to classification of fit for purpose.</p>

<p>Conclusion 2: My scarpas didn&#8217;t rub my ankle despite the physio foam donuts i normally wear in them.</p>

<p>Conclusion 3: I love getting to the car 5 minutes before a heavy downpour. It means I planned the walk perfectly ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
